# **DUNCAN J. MAYER, Ph.D.**

Doylestown Pennsylvania, 18901

609.571.5739 · DuncanMayer77@gmail.com

Personal Website · Github · LinkedIn · ORCID

#### PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

I am a social scientist and statistician with experience designing, managing, and leading research and evaluation portfolios with academic, government, and nonprofit stakeholders across a range of policy areas. I excel at research dissemination and have communicated results and recommendations to audiences with a range of technical sophistication.

#### **SKILLS**

Quantitative Longitudinal Data Analysis, Hierarchical Models, Spatial Statistics, Bayesian Methodologies

Qualitative: Focus Groups, Interviews, Content Analysis, and Case Studies

**Programming:** R (9 years) | SQL (4 years) | Stan (4 years)

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# **US Citizenship and Immigration Services, Department of Homeland Security**

Social Science Analyst (full-time)

Camp Springs, MD

August 2024 – Present

As a social scientist in USCIS's Policy Research and Evaluation Division I led retrospective and prospective studies of policy changes within the US immigration system. Among others, I worked with large and complex administrative data, and teams with diverse backgrounds, to evaluate changes to work authorization and the civics naturalization exam. I disseminated results in papers and briefed agency leadership on study findings.

BeVera Solutions Atlanta, GA

Health Statistician (full-time)

Sept. 2022 - August 2024

In a client facing role as a statistician at a consulting firm I contributed to project proposals, provided statistical support and consultation, and led and managed the methodological development of studies addressing internal questions for the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. I collaborated with CDC staff to elicit important questions, led outcome evaluations of COVID19 vaccine programs within federal agencies and studies of health equity during the nation's COVID19 vaccine roll out.

#### **Case Western Reserve University**

Research fellow (full-time)

Cleveland, OH Aug. 2018 – June. 2022

As a research fellow with the Center on Poverty and Community Development I developed and led a research portfolio focused on novel quantitative methodologies, program evaluation, and empirical studies of the distribution of community resources using modern computational methods. I delivered technical assistance, methodological support, and consultation for a range of evaluative projects for governments and nonprofit stakeholders. I lead the analysis of process and outcome evaluations of community health and pre-kindergarten programs, and contributed to evaluation capacity building projects within regional nonprofits. I disseminated the results of these projects in academic journals and presentations to academic and external audiences.

# The Institute for Public Policy and Economic Development

Wilkes-Barre, PA

Research Analyst (full-time)

July 2017 – June 2018

As a research analyst at a community based research organization I co-authored and led data analysis for funded research and evaluation projects including an analysis of the region's workforce trends using model-based projections of workforce needs, an impact evaluation of apprenticeship and early education programs using administrative data, and out-migration of college graduates using survey data. I ran focus

groups as part of needs assessments for the United Way and the Area Agency on Aging. I regularly provided consultation and technical assistance to health and human service oriented nonprofits and foundations, including evaluation capacity building by developing implementation and monitoring plans.

### **Marywood University**

Scranton, PA

Research Assistant (part-time)

January 2017 - July 2017

While completing a masters degree I provided quantitative methodological support for a case control study, with a probability sample, of behavioral interventions and expulsion rates in childcare centers across northeast Pennsylvania. I managed the study's data collection, including administrative and survey data, led data analysis and visualization.

# United Way of Lackawanna, Wayne, and Pike Counties

Scranton, PA

Community Impact Intern (Part-time)

Sept. 2016 - June 2017

While completing a masters degree I worked with the region's United Way to provide technical assistance to grantees, enhancing their data capture and evaluation efforts. I analyzed educational assessments for change over time, educated partners on census products to understand the region, and developed briefs and primers for task forces focused on a range of social and health issues.

# The Institute for Public Policy and Economic Development

Wilkes-Barre, PA

Research Intern (Part-time)

Dec. 2016 – June 2017

In the time between finishing my bachelors and beginning my masters degree, I worked with a community based research organization and contributed to funded research projects by collecting and analyzing survey data related to child welfare workforce development and job satisfaction, and developing literature reviews related to kindergarten truancy and the effect of the coal economy on northeast Pennsylvania.

# **United Neighborhood Centers of Northeast Pennsylvania**

Scranton, PA

Social Work Intern (Part-time)

Dec. 2015 – June 2016

During course work for a bachelors degree I worked with a local human service agency providing case management for clients in emergency situations such as utility shut-offs, eviction, and foreclosure.

### **Prevention Point Philadelphia**

Philadelphia, PA

Social Work Intern (Full-time)

May. 2015 - August 2015

While completing a bachelors degree I worked with a community health organization focused on harm reduction and substance use. I provided case management to a rotating caseload of 5-10 clients in a medication assisted treatment program, distributed resources for wound care and safe injection, and helped manage inventory in the syringe exchange program.

#### **EDUCATION**

Case Western Reserve University PhD in Social Welfare Dissertation: Essays on Community-Organization Dynamics	Cleveland, OH August 2023
Marywood University Masters of Social Work  Thesis: Evaluation Capacity; Structures, Stakeholders, Attitudes, and Environment	Scranton, PA May 2017
Bachelors of Social Work	May 2015
SELECT HONORS	
Case Western Reserve University Social Justice Institute Research Fellow	2022-2023
Association for Research on Nonprofit Organizations and Voluntary Action Doctoral Fellow	2022
Jack, Joseph and Morton Mandel School of Applied Social Sciences Research Fellow	2018-2022

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

#### **Peer-Reviewed Publications**

**Mayer, D. J.** (2024). Risk Society on Rails: Area Deprivation and Train Accidents Involving Hazardous Materials. *Enviornmental Justice*. DOI: 10.1089/env.2024.0009

**Mayer, D. J.** (2024). Connecting Founding and Dissolution; A Demographic Study of The US Nonprofit Sector. *Public Administration Review.* DOI: 10.1111/puar.13825

**Mayer, D. J.** (2024). Spatial Patterns of Nonprofit Founding; Toward a Local Ecology. *Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly*. DOI: 10.1177/08997640241230871

**Mayer, D. J.** (2024). Lead and Delinquency Rates; A Spatio-Temporal Perspective. *Social Science and Medicine*. DOI: 10.1016/j.socscimed.2023.116513

**Mayer, D. J.**, Groza, V. (2023). Promoting Children's Rights in Program Evaluation. *American Journal of Evaluation*. DOI: 10.1177/10982140221134621

**Mayer, D. J.**, Fischer, R. L. (2023). Teaching Spatial Data Analysis; A Case Study with Recommendations. *Nonprofit Policy Forum*. DOI: 10.1515/npf-2022-0044

**Mayer, D. J.** (2023). Understanding Location and Density; A Spatial Analysis of Cuyahoga County Ohio's Nonprofit Sector. *Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly*. DOI: 10.1177/08997640231171074

**Mayer, D. J.**, Fischer, R. L. (2023). Exploring Niche Alteration in Nonprofit Organizations. *Administration and Society*. DOI: 10.1177/00953997231165255

**Mayer, D. J.** (2023). Social Capital and the Nonprofit Infrastructure; An Ecological Study of Child Maltreatment. *Journal of Community Psychology*. DOI: 10.1002/jcop.22984

**Mayer, D. J.** (2023). Understanding Social Disorganization and the Nonprofit Infrastructure; An Ecological Study of Child Maltreatment Rates. *Social Currents*. DOI: 10.1177/23294965231159317

**Mayer, D. J.**, Fischer, R. L. (2023). Exploring Data Use in Nonprofit Organizations. *Evaluation and Program Planning*. DOI: 10.1016/j.evalprogplan.2022.102197

**Mayer, D. J.** (2022). Simmer Down Now! A Study of Revenue Volatility and Dissolution in Nonprofit Organizations. *Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly*. DOI: 10.1177/08997640221126147

**Mayer, D. J.**, Fischer, R. L. (2022). Can a Measurement Error Perspective Improve Estimation in Neighborhood Effects Research? A Hierarchical Bayesian Methodology. *Social Science Quarterly*. DOI: 10.1111/ssqu.13190

# **Working Papers**

Environmental Justice through Organization: Nonprofits and the Reduction of Childhood Lead Exposure Revealed Preference for Nonprofit Organizations: A Hedonic Price Analysis

#### **Book Chapters and Reviews**

Fischer, R. L., **Mayer, D. J.** (2022) Nonprofit Management: Beyond Managerialism. In W. Brown, M. Hale (eds). *Preparing Nonprofit Leaders: Contemporary Perspectives.* Routledge. ISBN: 9781032277806

Fischer, R. L., **Mayer, D. J.** (2020). Macro Social Work Practice: Working for Change in a Multicultural Society. *Journal of Teaching in Social Work*. DOI: 10.1080/08841233.2020.1809257

#### **Select Public Facing Professional or Technical Reports**

Fischer, R., Mansoor, D., **Mayer, D. J.** (2020). A Study of the Educational Needs of Fundraising and Grant Making Professionals in Northeast Ohio.

Atwell, M., Fischer, R., L., Chan, T, **Mayer, D. J.**, Henderson, M. (2019). Year Two Gap Analysis: Accountable Health Communities. The Center on Poverty and Community Development.

Ooms, T., Chew, A., **Mayer, D. J.** (2018). Senior Needs Assessment: 2018. Wilkes-Barre, PA: The Institute for Public Policy and Economic Development.

Ooms, T., Chew, A., **Mayer, D. J.**, Ritter, C. (2018). Berwick Community Needs Assessment. Wilkes-Barre, PA: The Institute for Public Policy and Economic Development.

Ooms, T., Chew, A., McCormick, E., **Mayer, D. J.** (2018). The Intersection of Transit and Land Use. Wilkes-Barre, PA: The Institute for Public Policy and Economic Development.

Ooms, T., Chew, A., **Mayer, D. J.**, McCormick, E. (2018). Social Determinants of Health. Wilkes-Barre, PA: The Institute for Public Policy and Economic Development.

Ooms, T., Chew, A., **Mayer, D. J.**, McCormick, E. (2018). Health Literacy: A Public Health Challenge. Wilkes-Barre, PA: The Institute for Public Policy and Economic Development.

Ooms, T., Chew, A., **Mayer, D. J.**, McCormick, E. (2018). What's Next? A Technical Report on 2018 Post-Graduation Polls. Wilkes-Barre, PA: The Institute for Public Policy and Economic Development.

Ooms, T., Chew, A., **Mayer, D. J.**, McCormick, E. (2018). The Nonprofit Social Service Sector in Luzerne and Lackawanna Counties. Wilkes-Barre, PA: The Institute for Public Policy and Economic Development.

Ooms, T., Chew, A., McCormick, E., **Mayer, D. J.** (2018). Workforce Trends and Challenges in Northeastern Pennsylvania. Wilkes-Barre, PA: The Institute for Public Policy and Economic Development.

Ooms, T., Chew, A., McCormick, E., **Mayer, D. J.** (2018). The Behavioral Health Initiative: A Report on the Behavioral Health Workforce. Wilkes-Barre, PA: The Institute for Public Policy and Economic Development.

Ooms, T., Chew, A., McCormick, E., **Mayer, D. J.** (2017). Public Policy and Civic Engagement: A Technical Report on 2017 Polls. Wilkes-Barre, PA: The Institute for Public Policy and Economic Development.

Mayer, D. J. (2017). Preschool and Dibels Assessments. Scranton, PA: United Way of Lackawanna and Wayne Counties.

#### **MEDIA**

"Mandel School's Duncan Mayer, Victor Groza write paper on children's rights in program evaluation", featured in Case Western Reserve University's "the Daily." September 1st, 2023.

"Mandel School's Duncan Mayer explores nonprofit location and density", featured in Case Western Reserve University's "the Daily." June 23rd, 2023.

"Mandel School's Duncan Mayer writes about child maltreatment", featured in Case Western Reserve University's "the Daily." May 12th, 2023.

"Duncan Mayer writes about revenue volatility", featured in Case Western Reserve University's "the Daily." December 2nd, 2022.

#### **PRESENTATIONS**

#### **Presentations at National Conferences**

**Mayer, D. J.** (2022, accepted but not presented). Understanding Social Disorganization and the Nonprofit Infrastructure; An Ecological Study of Child Maltreatment Rates. The Society for Social Work Research. Juried poster presentation.

**Mayer, D. J.** (2022). Revealed Preference for Nonprofit Organizations; A Hedonic Price Analysis. Annual Conference of the Association for Research on Nonprofit Organizations and Voluntary Action (ARNOVA). Juried paper presentation.

**Mayer, D. J.** (2022). Nonprofit Response to Neighborhood Conditions: Incorporating Space-Time Heterogeneity. Annual Conference of the Association for Research on Nonprofit Organizations and Voluntary Action (ARNOVA). Juried paper presentation.

**Mayer, D. J.**, Fischer, R. L. (2021). Examining Revenue Volatility in Nonprofit Organizations with a Discussion of Measurement and Portfolio Representation. Annual Conference of the Association for Research on Nonprofit Organizations and Voluntary Action (ARNOVA). Juried paper presentation.

#### **Presentations at Local Conferences**

**Mayer, D. J.** (2022). Understanding the Geography of Cuyahoga County's Nonprofit Sector Through Form-990 Data. Data Days Cleveland. Juried oral presentation.

**Mayer, D. J.** (2017). Evaluation Capacity: Structures, Stakeholders, Attitudes, and Environment. Annual Conference of the National Association of Social Workers, Pennsylvania. Juried poster presentation.

#### TEACHING (AND RELATED) EXPERIENCE

#### **Instructor of Record**

Case Western Reserve University

Evidence-informed practice (SASS 528)

Theoretical contexts shaping community practice

(SASS 534)

Poverty, wealth building, and social entrepreneurship

(SASS 367)

#### **Course Development**

Case Western Reserve University

Working with data for organizational empowerment

(SASS 500)

Community practice policy: Analyzing and changing

social policy (SASS 561)

### **Teaching Assistant**

Case Western Reserve University

Masters of Social Work: 2021 (in-person), 2022 (online)

Masters of Social Work: 2021 (online), 2022 (in-person)

Social Work Minor: 2020 (online)

Masters of Social Work, Certificate in Data Sciences for Social Impact, Approved 2021 Masters of Social Work, Approved 2020 (online)

Data-based decision making (SASS 410)	Masters of Nonprofit Organizations, 2020 (online)
Theoretical contexts shaping community practice (SASS 534)	Masters of Social Work, 2019-2021 (online/in-person)
Community practice policy: Analyzing and changing social policy (SASS 561)	Masters of Social Work, 2019-2021 (online/in-person)
Marywood University Social work research: Implementation and analysis (SW 702)	Masters of Social Work, 2017 (in-person)
SERVICE AND LEADERSHIP	

Case Western Reserve University Social Welfare PhD Executive Committee

2017-2019

Case Western Reserve University Masters of Social Work Community Practice Curriculum Committee

2019

**Ad hoc Reviewer:** Nonprofit Management and Leadership, City and Community, Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly, Public Performance and Management, Evaluation and Program Planning